Recreational Services and Athletics fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Recreational Services and Athletics fonds
1960 - 1995
F-80
3.5 m of textual records 62 moving images
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Fonds includes 62 moving images on 34 film reels (some moving image productions include multiple reels) and 39 videocassettes. All moving images are located in series 11.
Recreational Services and Athletics
The origins of Recreational Services and Athletics can be traced to two predecessor bodies established during the founding of the University in 1965. These bodies, the Athletics Program and the Recreation Program, were originally components of the Physical Development Centre, one of three centres that comprised the Faculty of Education. The organization of the Centre, approved by the Board of Governors on 14 January 1965, consisted of a Chairman acting as Head, responsible to the Dean of Education. Responsible to the Chairman were three Directors who oversaw the Centre's program areas of athletics, recreation, and research and professional development.
The Athletic Program was responsible for providing an opportunity to qualified students to increase their standards of athletic proficiency through competition in intercollegiate sports. Initially, the University competed on an intercollegiate level in three sports -- football, basketball and aquatic sports. Intercollegiate competition in other sports was added to the Program when interest and resources permitted. In contrast, the Recreation Program was responsible for providing a broad range of activities to students, faculty, staff, and the off-campus community through sport clubs, intramurals, community recreation programs and non-credit workshops and activity courses.
Reorganization within the Physical Development Centre, in 1967, resulted in the formation of the Physical Development Studies Department (later Kinesiology) and the merger of Athletics and Recreation as the Department of Athletics and Recreational Services. In 1970, responsibility for the Department of Athletics and Recreational Services was transferred from the Centre and the Faculty of Education to the Vice-President, Administration. In 1971, the VP, Administration divided the Department into three new departments: Athletics, Recreation, and Athletic and Recreational Services. Athletic and Recreational Services was headed by a Manager who reported to the Director of Ancillary Services and was responsible for the maintenance of athletic and recreational facilities and for the servicing of both the Athletics and Recreation Departments for such things as secretarial services, physiotherapy, audio-visual requirements, purchasing, equipment, ticket sales, transportation, accommodations, temporary help, scheduling, budget control, building and playfield maintenance and for all general administration. The Departments of Athletics and Recreation were headed by Directors who reported directly to the VP, Administration. Athletics remained responsible for intercollegiate sports, and Recreation for all other sports and leisure activities.
Slight changes to the above reporting structure occurred in 1979 when responsibility for the Department of Athletic and Recreational Services was transferred from the Director of Ancillary Services to the Directors of Athletics and Recreation. Reorganization occurred again in 1984 when the Departments of Athletics and Recreation were amalgamated to form the Department of Athletics and Recreation. This structure remained stable until 1996 when the Department of Athletics and Recreation merged with the Department of Athletic and Recreational Services to form the current Department of Recreational Services and Athletics.
Placement of the Department of Recreational Services and Athletics and its predecessors within the organizational hierarchy of the University have also undergone some changes over their history. As stated above, the Department(s) were originally located in the Physical Development Centre of the Faculty of Education and later transferred to the Vice-President, Administration. In 1986, the Department of Athletics and Recreation began reporting to the new office of the Executive Director of Administrative Services, a successor to the Vice-President, Administration. This office reverted to its former title of VP, Administration in 1990. In 1996, the Department was made a division of Campus Community Services which in turn was responsible to the Dean and Registrar of Student Services. The Dean and Registrar of Student Services reports to the Vice-President, Academic. This placement represents the current status of Recreational Services and Athletics.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on provenance.
Fonds consists of records created by the predecessor bodies of Recreational Services and Athletics. Activities and topics documented include the development of departmental policies, and objectives; the maintenance of facilities; departmental and university committees; the intercollegiate athletics program; the recreation program; the operation of athletic and recreational workshops and courses; departmental publications and publicity; and the responsibilities and operations of the Sports Information Office.
The predominant document types that comprise the fonds include correspondence; policy and procedure statements; agendas and minutes; reports; proposals; travel itineraries; schedules; rosters; statistics; news releases; press clippings; programs; newsletters; posters; films; and photographic material.
The records comprising the fonds were in considerable disorder when received by the Archives and Records Management Department. In order to provide access to the material, the archivist created series based on the functions and activities of the Department. The archivist also grouped loose material into file folders where necessary. Square brackets indicate file titles and dates supplied by the archivist. Furthermore, the archivist reintegrated into the fonds athletic and recreational material from collections that had been previously processed by the archives.
While records are grouped into series based on functions and activities of the Department, it should be noted that there is a considerable mixture of subjects and document types within each series. Therefore, researchers may have to search several series to locate records of interest.
Dinning, Michael; Davies, Lorne W.; Kirchner, Glenn; Moving images; Textual records; Sports, recreation and leisure
The records were acquired from the Department of Athletics and Recreation in a number of accessions.
Additional material has been accessioned but not yet processed (as of January 2006: 2.67 m., 1965-1985). Please consult the archivist for information about using these materials; restrictions may apply. Further accruals are expected.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details. Access to moving images is restricted due to the fragility of the original film reels
Complete file lists are available.
- Administration and organization records, 1960 - 1987; F-80-1; 12 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records related to the general administration and organization of the Department of Athletics and Recreation and its predecessors. Activities and topics documented include the development of departmental goals, objectives, policies, and philosophies; and the establishment of office and staff regulations and procedures. Predominant document types include correspondence, policy and procedure statements and handbooks (and other similar reference material), organizational charts, and minutes of departmental staff meetings.
  Files within the series annotated, collected file, indicate an artificial grouping created by a former archivist. Records within these files may have been collected from sources outside the fonds.
  - [Faculty of Education conference], 1965; F-80-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Athletic policies, 1966 - 1973; F-80-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - [Athletic staff policies], [ca 1960] - [ca 1969]; F-80-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - [Athletic policies], 1970; F-80-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - [Athletic policies: collected file], 1970; F-80-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - [Minutes of Department of Athletics staff meetings], 1970; F-80-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - [Correspondence: collected file], 1971 - 1973; F-80-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - Senate motion, 1975 - 1976; F-80-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - Goals and objectives; revenue, 1975 - 1985; F-80-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
    Restricted in part
  - [Policies and reports], 1977 - 1985; F-80-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - Policies and Procedures Handbook and revision, 1980 - 1985; F-80-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - [Policies and Procedures Handbook], 1985; F-80-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - Correspondence not filed, 1984 - 1987; F-80-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
- Facility records, 1973 - 1989; F-80-2; 8 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records related to proposed and actual athletic and recreational facilities, including government funded athletic training centres, a winter sports complex/ice arena, the Sports Medicine Clinic, the Outdoor Recreation Centre, and the Aquatic Centre. Activities and topics documented include planning and maintaining athletic and recreational facilities; and managing personnel. Predominant document types include correspondence, reports/proposals, a feasibility study, and a facility and budget questionnaire.
  - [Ice arena papers and reports: collected file], 1973; F-80-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 80-1)
  - [Winter Sports Complex Feasibility Study], 1973; F-80-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
    Pending review
  - Ice Rink Committee, 1973 - 1974; F-80-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - Sports Medicine Clinic/Training Room, 1977 - 1983; F-80-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - [Correspondence with Ministers of Sport], 1980 - 1983; F-80-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - Outdoor Recreation Centre, 1984 - 1985; F-80-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - SFU Aquatic Centre, 1985 - 1988; F-80-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - Sports Medicine Clinic, 1986; F-80-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - SFU Facility, budget questionnaire, 1986; F-80-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - [Report on the Development and Implementation of a Revenue Producing Plan for Full-Time Employment of Sports Information Officer], [ca 1980] - [ca 1989]; F-80-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
- Reports and related material, 1969 - 1990; F-80-3; 14 cm of textual records
  Series consists of various reports produced by or related to the Department of Athletics and Recreation. Activities and topics documented include departmental reviews; relations of SFU with the Canadian Intercollegiate Athletic Union and the Canada West University Athletic Association; the academic performance of SFU athletes; and athletics in Canadian universities. Predominant document types include reports and supporting documentation such as correspondence, press clippings, and government publications.
  Access to certain files containing student information has been restricted in accordance with Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy legislation. Consult the unit list and the archivist for further information.
  - [Prospective Growth and Reorganization of the Department of Athletics and Recreational Services within the Faculty of Education], 1969 - 1970; F-80-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - Department growth, 1969 - 1972; F-80-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - Green Paper on Amateur Sport by Iona Campagnolo, 1969 - 1977; F-80-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - [Reports reviewing the Department of Athletics and Recreational Services and the Department of Athletics: collected file], 1970 - 1977; F-80-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - Activities reports - Athletic Department, 1972 - 1977; F-80-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - Dr. A. W. Matthews Report: Athletics in Canadian Universities, 1973 - 1974; F-80-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 80-2)
  - Athletic Department annual report, 1974 - 1975; F-80-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - [Department of Recreation annual reports: collected file], 1974 - 1984; F-80-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - [History of the Department of Athletics and relations with the CIAU and the CWUAA], 1978; F-80-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - Wilson Report (academic performance of SFU athletes), 1975 - 1988; F-80-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
    Restrict in part
  - [Department of Recreation Annual Report], 1979 - 1980; F-80-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - [Resource Distribution in Athletics at SFU: Sexual Discrimination], [ca 1970] - [ca 1979]; F-80-3-0-0-12; Report found to be missing during the week of February 7, 2005. A photocopy of the report was made from a photocopy held by Hugh Johnston, SFU History professor, and inserted into the file. The location of the original is unknown. (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - [Executive Fitness Report (recreation)], 1981; F-80-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - [Athletic and Recreation Department Study], 1982; F-80-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - [Department of Recreation Annual Report], 1984 - 1985; F-80-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - [Participation in Recreation], 1984; F-80-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - [Department of Athletics Annual Report], 1982; F-80-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - Athletic and Recreational Services [annual report and related material], 1988 - 1990; F-80-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - Report of the committee on Intercollegiate Athletics, 1971; F-80-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
- Committee records, 1965 - 1984; F-80-4; 15 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records related to a number of committees established to review issues affecting the activities of Athletics and Recreation. These committees include the Visiting Committee on Athletics; the Student Affairs Committee; the Athletic Review Committee; the Athletics and Recreational Advisory Committee; and the Committee on Secondary Physical Education. Predominant document types include correspondence, agendas and minutes, reports, and tabled supporting documentation.
  - Visiting Committee on Athletics, 1965; F-80-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - Student Affairs Committee, 1968 - 1970; F-80-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - Athletic Review Committee #1, 1971; F-80-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - Athletic Review Committee #2, 1971; F-80-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 80-3)
  - Athletics and Recreational Advisory Committee, 1974 - 1977; F-80-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 80-4)
  - Athletics and Recreational Advisory Committee, 1977 - 1978; F-80-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 80-4)
  - Athletics and Recreational Advisory Committee, 1978 - 1981; F-80-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 80-4)
  - Athletics and Recreational Advisory Committee, 1982 - 1983; F-80-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 80-4)
  - Committee on Secondary Physical Education, 1983 - 1984; F-80-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 80-4)
  - Athletics and Recreational Advisory Committee, 1983 - 1984; F-80-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 80-4)
- Intercollegiate athletic records, 1965 - 1991; F-80-5; 1 m of textual records
  Series consists of records related to the operation of the intercollegiate athletics program. Activities and topics documented include general operations and concerns; operations of the sports teams comprising the intercollegiate program; and the granting of athletic awards and honours.
  Files within the series annotated, collected file, indicate an artificial arrangement imposed by a former archivist. Records within these files may have been collected from sources outside the fonds.
  Access to certain files containing student information has been restricted in accordance with Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy legislation. Consult the unit list and the archivist for further information
  - Intercollegiate athletic records - general, 1969 - 1987; F-80-5-1; 12 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of records related to the general operation of the intercollegiate athletics program. Activities and topics documented include booster club organization and fundraising; coaching duties and responsibilities; the establishment of and participation in the Evergreen Conference; budgetary allocations; athlete grade analysis; and academic counseling. Predominant document types include correspondence, travel itineraries, schedules, minutes, membership lists, athlete lists, constitutions, reports, proposals, study skills handouts, grade point average statistics, and an athletic survey.
    - Royal Order of Kilts, 1969; F-80-5-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Steudairs, 1969 - 1971; F-80-5-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Coaches workload, 1973 - 1974; F-80-5-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Athletic survey, 1977; F-80-5-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - BC Lions/SFU Clan Pep Team, 1977; F-80-5-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - List of SFU athletes, 1977 - 1978; F-80-5-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
      Restricted in whole
    - Athletics: highlights of 79-80 for all sports, 1979 - 1980; F-80-5-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Evergreen Conference, 1980 - 1981; F-80-5-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - [Sports expenses: a summary], 1981 - 1983; F-80-5-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - 81-82 athletes, 1981 - 1982; F-80-5-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Evergreen Conference, 1982; F-80-5-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Endowment campaign, 1983; F-80-5-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Perry Franklin: academic counseling, 1984; F-80-5-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Athletes grade analysis/eligibility, 1983 - 1986; F-80-5-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Academic advice, 1983 - 1987; F-80-5-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
  - Basketball records, 1965 - 1991; F-80-5-2; 16 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of records related to the operation of the men's and women's intercollegiate basketball program. Activities and topics documented include the recording of team statistics and records; travel; liaison with the National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics and member universities; and outreach to the local community. Predominant document types include correspondence, rosters, schedules, travel itineraries, statistics, press clippings, news releases, programs (game and season), press guides, and newsletters.
    Records related to the operation of the intercollegiate basketball program may also be found in the following series: Schedules; Workshop and Course Records; Publication and Publicity Records; and Sports Information Office Files.
    - Basketball, 1965 - 1966; F-80-5-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 80-5)
    - Basketball, 1969 - 1974; F-80-5-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Women's basketball, 1972 - 1973; F-80-5-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Men's basketball, 1975 - 1976; F-80-5-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Women's basketball, 1976 - 1977; F-80-5-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Basketball, 1976 - 1977; F-80-5-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Men's basketball, 1980 - 1981; F-80-5-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Women's basketball, 1980 - 1981; F-80-5-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Women's basketball, 1982 - 1984; F-80-5-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Men's basketball, 1982 - 1984; F-80-5-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Men's basketball, 1988 - 1990; F-80-5-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 80-6)
    - Buchanan Cup, 1987 - 1989; F-80-5-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Varsity Basketball (a report), 1986; F-80-5-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Women's basketball, 1988 - 1991; F-80-5-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
  - Football records, 1965 - 1990; F-80-5-3; 22 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of records related to the operation of the men's intercollegiate football program. Activities and topics documented include the recording of team statistics and records; travel; liaison with the National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics, the Columbia Football League, and member universities; relations with the Canadian Intercollegiate Athletics Union and the Canada West University Athletic Association; relations with the Canadian Football League; operations of the Clan Alumni Club; and the staging of the annual Shrum Bowl. Predominant document types include correspondence, minutes, rosters, schedules, travel itineraries, statistics, press clippings, news releases, programs (game and season), press guides, and newsletters.
    Records related to the operation of the intercollegiate football program may also be found in the following series: Schedules; Workshop and Course Records; Publication and Publicity Records; and Sports Information Office Files.
    - [Football], 1965; F-80-5-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Football, 1966; F-80-5-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Football statistics, 1967; F-80-5-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Football statistics, 1968; F-80-5-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Football recruiting, 1968; F-80-5-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Canadian Football League, 1968 - 1979; F-80-5-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Football, 1971 - 1972; F-80-5-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Football, 1976 - 1977; F-80-5-3-0-8 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - CFL proposal, 1977 - 1978; F-80-5-3-0-9 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1980; F-80-5-3-0-10 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Football, 1980 - 1981; F-80-5-3-0-11 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1981; F-80-5-3-0-12 (Archival box - standard 80-7)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1982; F-80-5-3-0-13 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Football, 1982 - 1984; F-80-5-3-0-14 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1983; F-80-5-3-0-15 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1984; F-80-5-3-0-16 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1985 - 1986; F-80-5-3-0-17 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Clan Alumni Football Club, 1986 - 1989; F-80-5-3-0-18 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1987; F-80-5-3-0-19 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1988; F-80-5-3-0-20 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Men's football, 1988 - 1989; F-80-5-3-0-21 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - Shrum Bowl, 1989; F-80-5-3-0-22 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
    - CIAU, 1989 - 1990; F-80-5-3-0-23 (Archival box - standard 80-8)
  - Soccer records, 1969 - 1991; F-80-5-4; 11 cm of textual records